Birthday Puja 1984-0322, Bombay (India)
Doğum Günü Pujası 1984-0322, Bombay (Hindistan)
I have just told them (Indian Sahaja Yogis) that you should not try to copy
Onlara (Hintli Sahaja Yogiler) az önce,
the western style of ego-oriented society where people use harsh words,
insanların sert sözler kullandığı, ego odaklı batı tarzı toplumu taklit etmeye çalışmamaları gerektiğini söyledim,
because then we think that we have modernized ourselves, you see.
çünkü o zaman kendimizi modernleştirdiğimizi düşünürüz, anlarsınız.
To say harsh words to somebody, “What do I care! I hate you!”
Birine sert sözler söylemek, "Ne umurumda ki! Senden nefret ediyorum!"
All these sentences we have never used, you see, which is unknown to us.
Bu tür cümleleri hiç kullanmadık, bu bizim için bilinmeyen bir şey.
I mean, anybody to say like that is unmannerliness.
Yani, siz böyle konuşursanız, bu kabalıktır.
How can you say such a thing: “I hate you!”?
Nasıl böyle bir şey söyleyebilirsin: "Senden nefret ediyorum!"
But now I have heard people talking like this in our country.
Ama şimdi ülkemizde insanların böyle konuştuğunu duyuyorum.
"I hate you." “What's wrong with us?” “Who are you to say that?”
"Senden nefret ediyorum." "Bizde yanlış olan ne ki?" "Sen kimsin ki böyle konuşuyorsun?"
Like that we don't talk. You see, this is not the way to talk at all.
Biz böyle konuşmayız. Görüyorsunuz, bu hiç de doğru bir konuşma tarzı değil.
Any person who comes from a good family
İyi bir aileden gelen hiç kimse böyle konuşmaz,
would not talk like this because it reflects on the family.
çünkü bu ailenin itibarını zedeler.
But the language is more copied here than there.
Ama burada dil, orada olduğundan daha fazla taklit ediliyor.
I am surprised sometimes when I hear the people [how] they talk
Bazen insanların otobüslerde, taksilerde,
in the buses, in the taxies, in the things;
çeşitli yerlerde nasıl konuştuklarını duyduğumda şaşırıyorum;
the way they use language is, you see, is something I can’t understand.
kullandıkları dil, siz anlarsınız ya, Benim anlayamadığım bir şey.
So I have asked them that the language should be full of love
Bu yüzden onlara dilin sevgi dolu
and with our own traditional style, the way...
ve kendi geleneksel tarzımızla, bizim tarzımızla olması gerektiğini söyledim ...
You see, we wouldn’t even scold our children.
Siz anlarsınız ya, çocuklarımızı bile azarlamayız.
If you have to scold the children, we use a language
Çocukları azarlamak zorunda kalırsak,
which makes them over honourable (Bahumanarthi):
onları onurlandıran bir dil kullanırız (Bahumanarthi):
[(Marathi)
[(Marathi)
Damle Sahab has put on a kurta pyjama, so, “You are looking like Shivaji Maharaj.
Damle Sahab, kurta pijama giymiş, bu yüzden, "Shivaji Maharaj'a benziyorsun.
Welcome Shivaji Maharaj”.
Hoş geldin, Shivaji Maharaj."
We should speak in such respectful language so that they would not get scared.
Onları korkutmamak için bu kadar saygılı bir dil kullanmalıyız.
Correction if it is to be done], we used to do it this way;
Düzeltme yapılması gerekiyorsa, biz böyle yapardık;
but the correction of the other side is not proper because that never it corrects.
ama diğer tarafın düzeltmesi doğru değildir çünkü bu asla düzeltmez.
You see, that’s why you cannot control your children.
Görüyorsunuz, bu yüzden çocuklarınızı kontrol edemezsiniz.
You are all the time insulting them, insulting others, insulting methods,
Siz sürekli onları aşağılıyorsunuz, başkalarını aşağılıyorsunuz, yöntemleri aşağılıyorsunuz,
you see, and this emotional blackmail and all this nonsense
görüyorsunuz, ve bu duygusal şantaj ve tüm bu saçmalıklar
is not at all traditional in this country.
bu ülkede hiç de geleneksel değildir.
And those who'll try to do it will be thrown out.
Ve bunu yapmaya çalışanlar kovulacaktır.
I can tell you, in Sahaja Yoga you cannot work out.
Size şunu söyleyebilirim, Sahaja Yoga'da çalışamazsınız.
You should not have all these ideas of insulting people,
İnsanları aşağılama, onları aşağılanabilecek durumlara
of bringing them into situations where they can be insulted. This is all modern style.
sokma gibi fikirleriniz olmamalı. Bunların hepsi modern tarz.
So we should not do like that in Sahaja Yoga.
Sahaja Yoga'da böyle davranmamalıyız.
We should behave in such a way that we should be dignified people.
Onurlu insanlar olacak şekilde davranmalıyız.
Behoving our style is our tradition, is Sahaja Yogis' tradition is this
Tarzımıza uygun davranmak bizim geleneğimizdir, Sahaja Yogilerin geleneğimizdir.
that we talk to people in the most sophisticated manner,
İnsanlarla en sofistike,
in the sweetest manner, in the most affectionate manner and inviting manner.
en tatlı, en sevgi dolu ve davetkar bir şekilde konuşuruz.
And that is how we all should speak. So, this is [the] first thing I ask
Hepimiz böyle konuşmalıyız. Bu yüzden, ilk olarak,
that in your expression of your love
sevginizi ifade ederken
there should not be a thing that you should shout.
bağırmamanızı rica ediyorum.
Now, I do shout at some people who have bhoots in them,
Şimdi, Ben içlerinde bhootlar olan bazı insanlara bağırırım,
but by that the bhoots run away. But if you shout, you get the bhoots.
ama bu sayede bhootlar kaçar. Ama siz bağırırsanız, bhootları alırsınız.
The bhoots don't run away, they get at you; so better not do it.
Bhootlar kaçmaz, size saldırır; bu yüzden bunu yapmamak daha iyidir.
If you have My powers you can do that; but you don’t have.
Benim güçlerime sahipseniz bunu yapabilirsiniz; ama sizde yok.
If you shout at the person who has bhoots, you get the bhoots.
Bhoots olan kişiye bağırırsanız, bhoots'ları alırsınız.
So be careful, don’t try My tricks. You see, I am a different type of a person
Bu yüzden dikkatli olun, Benim numaralarımı denemeyin. Görüyorsunuz, Ben farklı bir insanım
and I do everything so understandingly, which you do not.
ve Ben her şeyi anlayarak yaparım, siz ise yapmazsınız.
So, when you follow Me, you should follow Me the way I am,
Bu yüzden, Beni takip ettiğinizde, Beni olduğum gibi,
on the side where I forgive,
affettiğim tarafta, sevgi gösterdiğim şekilde takip etmelisiniz.
the way I am loving, I am affectionate; not where I am terrible.
sevgi dolu olduğum tarafta, korkunç olduğum tarafta değil.
You shouldn't do that because My terrible nature has got the undercurrent
Bunu yapmamalısınız, çünkü Benim korkunç doğamın altında
of My Love, which you don’t have, and you don’t have these powers.
Benim sevgimin akışı vardır, ki sizde yok ve siz bu güçlere sahip değilsiniz.
So don’t try those tricks with anybody else.
Bu yüzden bu numaraları başkasında denemeyin.
You have no right to shout at anyone or to get angry,
sizin hiç kimseye bağırmaya veya kızmaya hakkınız yok,
because if you shout, you get back all these bhoots into you.
çünkü bağırırsanız, tüm bu bhootlar size geri dönerler.
They want, they provoke you. They provoke you so that you get caught up into it
Onlar bunu istiyorlar, sizi kışkırtıyorlar. Sizleri kışkırtıyorlar ki,
and you get absolutely ruined, the more you try to do it.
bundan catch olup, ne kadar çok denerseniz o kadar çok mahvolursunuz.
So, the best thing is to stand in the centre and have affection and love -
Bu yüzden en iyisi merkezde durmak ve sevgi ve ilgi beslemektir -
the power that I have given you. That you have [to] develop - that power of love.
size verdiğim güç. Geliştirmeniz gereken şey - sevgi gücü.
First you develop that power of love. Then you don’t have to worry,
Önce sevgi gücünü geliştirin. O zaman endişelenmenize gerek kalmaz, bağırmanıza gerek kalmaz, hiçbir şey söylemenize gerek kalmaz.
you don’t have to shout, you don't have to say anything.
Gücünüz Krita (aktif) hale gelir, kendi kendine çalışır ve istediğimiz o güzel atmosferi yaratır. Bağırmanıza gerek kalmaz, hiçbir şey söylemenize gerek kalmaz.
Your power will become the Krita (active), it will work out itself
Gücünüz Krita (aktif) hale gelir, kendi kendine çalışır
and create that beautiful atmosphere that we want to do.
ve bizim istediğimiz o güzel atmosferi yaratır.
We don't want anybody to be ruined.
Kimsenin mahvolmasını istemiyoruz.
But if you start shouting at people, they’ll all run away.
Ama insanlara bağırmaya başlarsanız, hepsi kaçar.
Specially in the ego-oriented society, you should not shout at all!
Özellikle ego odaklı bir toplumda, hiç bağırmamalısınız!
That will not appeal to anyone.
Bu hiç kimseyi etkilemez.
If you shout at anyone in the ego-oriented society,
Ego odaklı bir toplumda birine bağırırsanız,
you will always distract them and they'll run away.
her zaman dikkatlerini dağıtırsınız ve kaçarlar.
So I have to tell you, that you might be the highest of highest,
Bu yüzden size şunu söylemeliyim, en yüksek olan siz olabilirsiniz,
first thing [that] you have to give Me today is that in your talk,
bugün gereken ilk şey [o] bugün Bana vermeniz gereken ilk şey,
in your behaviour, in your heart, you will reside one with Love.
sizin konuşmalarınızda, davranışlarınızda, kalbinizde sevgi ile bir olmanızdır.
And the second thing I want to ask is that you should be peaceful people.
Ve ikinci olarak sizden istediğim şey, huzurlu insanlar olmanızdır.
Try to have peace with yourself. Don’t fight with yourself.
Kendinizle barışık olmaya çalışın. Kendinizle savaşmayın.
Now, the western people have one problem [that] they fight with themselves.
Batılıların bir sorunu var, onlar kendileriyle savaşıyorlar.
“How is it this is happening to me? I am so bad. I am no good.
"Bu bana nasıl oluyor? çok kötüyüm. Ben iyi değilim.
I have done this. I am so bad.”
Bunu yaptım. Ben çok kötüyüm.
If you go on fighting with yourself, then you will become week.
Siz kendinizle kavga etmeye devam ederseniz, zayıf düşersiniz.
On the contrary, you must say, “I am so good. What’s wrong with me?
Aksine, "Ben çok iyiyim. Bende yanlış olan ne var ki?
I’ve got realization. What’s wrong with me?
Ben aydınlandım. Bende yanlış ne var ki?" demelisiniz.
Have that confidence in oneself, and then it will work out.
Kendinize bu kadar güvenin, o zaman her şey yoluna girecektir.
And as result of that only you start shouting at others.
Ve bunun sonucunda sadece başkalarına bağırmaya başlarsınız.
But supposing you understand
Ama kendinizde
that there is nothing wrong with you, you have to be peaceful.
bir sorun olmadığını anlarsanız, huzurlu olmalısınız.
We all have to be very peaceful people and you have seen,
Hepimiz çok huzurlu insanlar olmalıyız ve gördüğünüz gibi,
My peaceful nature has solved so many problems just like that.
Benim huzurlu tabiatım pek çok sorunu bu şekilde çözdü.
So try to achieve that peace within you. That peace should not be lost at any cost,
Öyleyse içinizdeki o huzuru elde etmeye çalışın. O huzur ne pahasına olursa olsun kaybedilmemeli
and should not be also expressed outside in a way, like I sometimes.
ve Benim bazen yaptığım gibi, dışarıya da yansıtılmamalı.
My peace itself becomes terrible.
Benim huzurum bile korkunç hale gelir.
But you don’t have that kind of a possibility, so you just don’t do it.
Ama sizde böyle bir olasılık yok, o yüzden siz bunu yapmayın.
You just don’t do it, never do it that way.
Sakın yapmayın, asla böyle yapmayın.
Try to be extremely peaceful, try to make your forehead relaxed.
Son derece huzurlu olmaya çalışın, alnınızı gevşetmeye çalışın.
Many people come to Me with [face] like this, you see,
Birçok insan Bana böyle bir yüzle gelir,
then I just know that there is a big bhoot on the head sitting;
o zaman onun kafasında büyük bir bhoot oturduğunu anlarım;
then I shout at them.
sonra Ben onlara bağırırım.
Keep your forehead relaxed, relaxed.
Alnınızı gevşetin, gevşetin.
“I am not doing anything, Mother is doing everything. Relax, relax, relax.”
"Ben hiçbir şey yapmıyorum, her şeyi Anne yapıyor, deyin. Gevşetin, gevşeyin, gevşeyin."
If you relax, you’ll find that your heart will open.
Gevşerseniz, kalbinizin açıldığını göreceksiniz.
“My heart cannot open.” Why, why can’t you open your heart?
"Kalbiniz açılmıyor. Neden, neden kalbinizi açamıyorsunuz?
Because you have no trust in yourself.
Çünkü kendinize güvenmiyorsunuz.
Try to trust yourself, open your Agnya, open your Ekadasha
Kendinize güvenmeye çalışın, Agnya'nızı açın, Ekadasha'nızı ve Sahasrara'nızı açın,
and your Sahasrara, and your heart will open. Once your Sahasrara is open,
ve kalbinizi açın. Bir kez Sahasrara'nız açıldığında,
your heart will open automatically, so you will have a peaceful life.
bu kalbinizi otomatik olarak açacaktır, bu sayede huzurlu bir hayatınız olacaktır.
So today I am asking for two things from you.
Bu yüzden bugün sizden iki şey istiyorum.
It's a funny thing that a Mother has to ask for a gift.
Bir annenin hediye istemek zorunda kalması komik bir şey.
And the gift you have to give - first one - is that you should be peaceful people.
Ve vermeniz gereken hediye - ilki – sizlerin huzurlu insanlar olmanızdır.
You should express peacefulness through your own character, talking.
Kendi karakterinizle, konuşmalarınızla huzurlu olduğunuzu ifade etmelisiniz.
But it doesn't mean that you should be people who are bleak,
Ama bu, kasvetli insanlar olmanız gerektiği anlamına gelmez,
or who are - we can say that - are morbid people
ya da - diyebiliriz ki – bu sizin marazlı insanlar ya da saçmalıkları tolere eden
or people who tolerate nonsense. No, there is a way of resistance.
insanlar olmanız gerektiği anlamına gelmez. Hayır, direnmenin bir yolu var.
But a resistance, of a peaceful resistance, that you are not afraid of anything;
Ama bu direnç, barışçıl bir direnç, hiçbir şeyden korkmamanız,
you are not frightened of anything; you are not going to bow down to anything;
hiçbir şeyden çekinmemeniz, hiçbir şeye boyun eğmemeniz,
you are not going to compromise with anything, but you are peaceful.
hiçbir şeyle uzlaşmamanız, ama barışçıl olmanızdır.
That sort of a temperament you must develop
Bu tür bir mizacı geliştirmeli
and also express outside, is very important.
ve dışarıda da ifade etmelisiniz, bu çok önemli.
And [the] second one is the..., this peace and all this
İkincisi ise... bu huzur ve tüm bunlar,
should express your love to others, love to others.
başkalarına olan sevginizi, başkalarına olan sevginizi ifade etmelidir.
Like now, everywhere, within next one or two years we'll have ashrams,
Şu anda olduğu gibi, bir veya iki yıl içinde aşramlarımız olacak,
I am sure of that. And in the ashram, I would like to see
bundan eminim. Ve aşramda,
people having loving, caring, affectionate, patronising,
oraya gelen insanlara karşı sevgi dolu, şefkatli,
beautiful attitude towards the people who come there.
sevecen, koruyucu, güzel bir tutum sergileyen insanlar görmek isterim.
On the contrary, if you do not have, your ashrams will be all reduced to zero.
Aksine, eğer böyle bir tutumunuz yoksa, aşramlarınızın hepsi sıfıra inecektir.
It has happened in many places; it will happen everywhere.
Bu birçok yerde oldu; her yerde olacak.
So, you don’t blame Me, “Why our ashrams don’t run good?”
Öyleyse, aşramlarımız çalışmıyor diye Beni suçlamayın.
It will be your responsibility to see that it is your Mother’s House
Orasının Annenizin Evi olduğunu ve insanların Annenizin Evi'ne
and people are coming to the Mother’s House. And how a Mother would treat
geldiğini görmek sizin sorumluluğunuzda olacaktır. Ve bir anne bu insanlara karşı sevgi,
these people with love, affection, with whatever you have.
şefkat ve sahip olduğunuz her şeyle nasıl davranırsa öyle davranın.
You can starve, but give to others, look after them.
Siz aç kalabilirsiniz, ama başkalarına verin, onlara bakın.
Give them all the kindness and sweetness, so the impression of people...
Onlara tüm nezaketinizi ve tatlılığınızı gösterin, böylece insanların izlenimi...
Even if you are slightest not like that, people will think,
En ufak bir şekilde bile öyle olmasanız bile, insanlar
"This is a very arrogant personality. And how can it be?"
"Bu çok kibirli bir kişilik. Ve bu nasıl olabilir?" diye düşüneceklerdir.
So you have to be a top class person to be in charge of an ashram.
Bu yüzden bir aşramın sorumluluğunu üstlenmek için, birinci sınıf bir insan olmalısınız.
If a person who is a mediocre, he should not appoint.
Vasat bir insan ise, bu konuma atanmamalıdır.
By God’s grace, I'm sure, by next year you'll have all the lands in your hand,
Tanrı'nın lütfuyla, eminim ki, gelecek yıl tüm topraklar elinizde olacak
and all your ashrams will start by next year in every country.
ve tüm ashramlarınız gelecek yıl her ülkede faaliyete geçecek.
May God bless you.
Tanrı sizleri kutsasın.
This is what I give you on My birthday today
Bugün doğum günümde sizlere verdiğim hediye,
that you all will have your ashrams properly established by the end of next year.
gelecek yılın sonuna kadar hepinizin ashramlarınızı düzgün bir şekilde kurmanızdır.
But first two things you must..., the conditions are there.
Ama önce iki şeyi yapmalısınız..., şartlar var.
First two conditions should be there. If you are not good for that,
İlk iki şart yerine getirilmelidir. Bunun için siz hazır değilseniz,
God will never give you an ashram,
Tanrı size asla bir aşram vermez,
because He doesn’t want to give ashram to some funny people.
çünkü O, tuhaf insanlara aşram vermek istemez.
It's become sort of a recluse for people who have no place anywhere
Aşram, hiçbir yere gelip oturamayan
[to] come and sit in the ashram.
insanlar için bir tür inziva yeri haline gelmiştir.
So unless and until you have people of that level,
Bu yüzden,
who will remain peaceful and loving, you will not establish.
huzurlu ve sevgi dolu kalacak bu düzeyde insanlar olmadıkça kurulamazsınız.
But if you do, I’m sure, by next year you should be able
Ama eğer yaparsanız, eminim ki gelecek yıl
to have ashrams in every place.
her yerde aşramlarınız olabilir.
May God Bless you.
Tanrı sizi kutsasın.